<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<aiml version="1.0">
<!-- Science and Nature - Made by Muqeet, Zaryab, Ali -->

<category><pattern>WHAT IS GRAVITY</pattern>
<template>Gravity is a fundamental force of nature that attracts any two objects with mass. It keeps you on Earth, the Moon orbiting Earth, and Earth orbiting the Sun. Discovered by Newton when an apple fell on his head (legend says).</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS PHOTOSYNTHESIS</pattern>
<template>Photosynthesis is how plants make food. They use sunlight, water, and carbon dioxide to produce glucose (sugar) and oxygen. It's basically plants being solar-powered chefs feeding the entire planet.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS DNA</pattern>
<template>DNA (Deoxyribonucleic Acid) is the molecule that contains your genetic code - like a biological instruction manual. It's shaped like a twisted ladder (double helix) and determines everything from your eye color to your height.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS AN ATOM</pattern>
<template>An atom is the smallest unit of matter. It consists of a nucleus (protons + neutrons) surrounded by electrons. Everything you see, touch, taste, and smell is made of atoms. You contain about 7 octillion of them!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A BLACK HOLE</pattern>
<template>A black hole is a region in space where gravity is so strong that nothing, not even light, can escape. They form when massive stars die and collapse. Time itself warps near them. Fascinating and terrifying!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS THE SUN</pattern>
<template>The Sun is a star - a massive ball of hydrogen and helium undergoing nuclear fusion. It's 4.6 billion years old, 109 times wider than Earth, and provides the energy that makes life on Earth possible.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS THE MOON</pattern>
<template>The Moon is Earth's only natural satellite, about 1/4 Earth's diameter. It controls our tides, stabilizes our axis, and has been visited by 12 humans. It's slowly drifting away at 3.8 cm per year!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A PLANET</pattern>
<template>A planet is a celestial body that orbits a star, is massive enough for gravity to make it round, and has cleared its orbital neighborhood. Our solar system has 8 planets (sorry, Pluto).</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A STAR</pattern>
<template>A star is a massive ball of gas (mainly hydrogen and helium) held together by gravity, producing energy through nuclear fusion. Our Sun is a star. Every element heavier than hydrogen was made in a star!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A GALAXY</pattern>
<template>A galaxy is a huge collection of stars, gas, dust, and dark matter held together by gravity. Our Milky Way contains 100-400 billion stars. There are about 2 trillion galaxies in the observable universe!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS THE MILKY WAY</pattern>
<template>The Milky Way is our home galaxy - a barred spiral galaxy about 100,000 light-years across containing our solar system. When you look at the night sky's "milky" band, you're looking at our galaxy's disk edge-on.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS EVOLUTION</pattern>
<template>Evolution is the process by which species change over generations through natural selection. Those best adapted to their environment survive and reproduce, passing traits to offspring. It explains life's diversity.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS CLIMATE CHANGE</pattern>
<template>Climate change refers to long-term shifts in global temperatures and weather patterns. Currently, human activities (burning fossil fuels, deforestation) are accelerating warming, causing rising seas and extreme weather.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS THE OZONE LAYER</pattern>
<template>The ozone layer is a region of Earth's stratosphere containing high concentrations of ozone (O3). It absorbs 97-99% of the Sun's harmful UV radiation, protecting life on Earth. CFCs once damaged it, but it's recovering.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS GLOBAL WARMING</pattern>
<template>Global warming is the long-term increase in Earth's average temperature due to greenhouse gases trapping heat. Since 1880, global temp has risen about 1.1°C. Effects include melting ice, rising seas, and extreme weather.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS ELECTRICITY</pattern>
<template>Electricity is the flow of electric charge (usually electrons) through a conductor. It powers everything from your phone to cities. It can be generated from fossil fuels, nuclear, solar, wind, and hydro sources.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS MAGNETISM</pattern>
<template>Magnetism is a force produced by moving electric charges, creating fields that attract or repel certain materials. Earth itself is a giant magnet! Magnets have north and south poles - opposites attract.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS LIGHT</pattern>
<template>Light is electromagnetic radiation visible to the human eye. It travels at 299,792 km/s - the universe's speed limit. It behaves as both a wave and a particle (photon). White light contains all colors of the rainbow.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS SOUND</pattern>
<template>Sound is a vibration that travels through matter (air, water, solids) as a wave. It can't travel in a vacuum (space is silent!). Humans hear frequencies between 20 Hz and 20,000 Hz.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS ENERGY</pattern>
<template>Energy is the ability to do work or cause change. It cannot be created or destroyed, only transformed. Forms include kinetic, potential, thermal, electrical, chemical, and nuclear. E=mc² shows mass is energy!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS MATTER</pattern>
<template>Matter is anything that has mass and takes up space. It exists in states: solid, liquid, gas, and plasma. All matter is made of atoms. Even you are matter - about 7 octillion atoms of it!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS WATER</pattern>
<template>Water (H2O) is a molecule of 2 hydrogen atoms and 1 oxygen. It's essential for all life, covers 71% of Earth's surface, and is the only substance found naturally in all three states. Your body is 60% water!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS AIR</pattern>
<template>Air is the mixture of gases in Earth's atmosphere: 78% nitrogen, 21% oxygen, and 1% other gases (argon, CO2, water vapor). It has mass, exerts pressure, and makes breathing possible!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS OXYGEN</pattern>
<template>Oxygen is a chemical element (O) essential for respiration. It makes up 21% of air and about 65% of human body mass (in water). It's produced by plants during photosynthesis. Highly reactive and supports combustion.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS CARBON</pattern>
<template>Carbon is the 6th element, the basis of all known life. It forms more compounds than any other element. Found in diamonds, graphite, coal, and every living thing. Life is "carbon-based."</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS HYDROGEN</pattern>
<template>Hydrogen is the simplest and most abundant element in the universe (75% of all matter). It powers stars through fusion. On Earth, it's found in water and organic compounds. Atomic number 1!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS NITROGEN</pattern>
<template>Nitrogen makes up 78% of Earth's atmosphere. It's essential for proteins and DNA. Most organisms can't use atmospheric nitrogen directly - bacteria convert it to usable forms (nitrogen fixation).</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS IRON</pattern>
<template>Iron is a metal essential for life - it carries oxygen in blood (hemoglobin). It's the most common element on Earth by mass and makes steel. Earth's core is mostly iron, creating our magnetic field.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS GOLD</pattern>
<template>Gold is a precious metal prized for its beauty and rarity. It doesn't corrode, is highly malleable, and conducts electricity. It's created in supernova explosions. All gold on Earth came from space!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS SILVER</pattern>
<template>Silver is a precious metal with the highest electrical and thermal conductivity of any element. Used in jewelry, electronics, and photography. It has antimicrobial properties and was once used as currency.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS COPPER</pattern>
<template>Copper is a metal known for excellent electrical conductivity - that's why electrical wiring is copper. It's been used for 10,000 years, gives the Statue of Liberty its color, and is essential for human health.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS URANIUM</pattern>
<template>Uranium is a radioactive metal used as fuel in nuclear reactors and weapons. It's naturally occurring and 40 times more common than silver. One kilogram can produce as much energy as 1,500 tons of coal!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS RADIATION</pattern>
<template>Radiation is energy traveling through space as waves or particles. Types include electromagnetic (light, X-rays) and ionizing (from radioactive decay). Some is harmless (radio waves), some dangerous (gamma rays).</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A CELL</pattern>
<template>A cell is the basic unit of life. All living things are made of cells. Human bodies have about 37 trillion! Cells contain DNA, perform metabolism, and can reproduce. There are two types: prokaryotic and eukaryotic.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A VIRUS</pattern>
<template>A virus is a microscopic infectious agent that can only replicate inside living cells. It's debated whether they're "alive." They cause diseases from common cold to COVID-19. They're much smaller than bacteria.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS BACTERIA</pattern>
<template>Bacteria are single-celled microorganisms found everywhere on Earth. Some cause disease, but most are harmless or beneficial. Your gut contains trillions of bacteria that help digestion. They were the first life on Earth!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A VACCINE</pattern>
<template>A vaccine is a biological preparation that provides immunity to a disease. It trains your immune system to recognize pathogens by using weakened, killed, or partial forms of the virus or bacteria.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS THE IMMUNE SYSTEM</pattern>
<template>The immune system is your body's defense against infections. It includes white blood cells, antibodies, and organs like the spleen. It remembers past infections to fight them faster next time.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A GENE</pattern>
<template>A gene is a segment of DNA that contains instructions for making a specific protein. Humans have about 20,000 genes. They determine traits like eye color, height, and susceptibility to diseases.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A CHROMOSOME</pattern>
<template>A chromosome is a structure of tightly coiled DNA containing many genes. Humans have 46 chromosomes (23 pairs). One set comes from each parent. Sex chromosomes (XX or XY) determine biological sex.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS THE BRAIN</pattern>
<template>The brain is the organ that controls all body functions and processes thoughts. It contains about 86 billion neurons and uses 20% of your body's energy. It's essentially 3 pounds of biology running your consciousness!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS THE HEART</pattern>
<template>The heart is a muscular organ that pumps blood throughout your body. It beats about 100,000 times a day, pumping 2,000 gallons of blood. It has 4 chambers and its own electrical system to keep rhythm.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS BLOOD</pattern>
<template>Blood is a bodily fluid that delivers nutrients and oxygen to cells and carries away waste. Adults have about 5 liters. It contains red cells, white cells, platelets, and plasma. There are 8 blood types.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A MUSCLE</pattern>
<template>Muscles are tissues that produce force and motion. Humans have over 600 muscles making up 40% of body weight. There are 3 types: skeletal (movement), smooth (organs), and cardiac (heart).</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A BONE</pattern>
<template>Bones are rigid organs forming the skeleton - providing structure, protecting organs, and producing blood cells. Adults have 206 bones. They're living tissue that constantly remodels. The femur is the longest.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS SKIN</pattern>
<template>Skin is the body's largest organ, covering about 2 square meters. It protects internal organs, regulates temperature, and enables touch sensation. It has 3 layers and completely replaces itself every 27 days!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS AN EARTHQUAKE</pattern>
<template>An earthquake is the shaking of Earth's surface caused by tectonic plates moving, breaking, or slipping past each other. Energy is released as seismic waves. Measured on the Richter or moment magnitude scale.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A VOLCANO</pattern>
<template>A volcano is an opening in Earth's crust through which molten rock (lava), ash, and gases escape. They form at plate boundaries or hotspots. Eruptions can be explosive or gentle. There are about 1,500 active volcanoes.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A TSUNAMI</pattern>
<template>A tsunami is a series of ocean waves caused by underwater earthquakes, volcanic eruptions, or landslides. They can travel at 500 mph in deep water and grow to 100+ feet tall when reaching shore.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A HURRICANE</pattern>
<template>A hurricane is a large, rotating storm system with wind speeds of 74+ mph, forming over warm ocean waters. Called typhoons in the Pacific and cyclones in the Indian Ocean. They can span 300+ miles wide.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A TORNADO</pattern>
<template>A tornado is a violently rotating column of air extending from a thunderstorm to the ground. Wind speeds can exceed 300 mph. The US averages 1,200 annually. They're ranked F0-F5 on the Fujita scale.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS THUNDER</pattern>
<template>Thunder is the sound caused by lightning. Lightning superheats air to 30,000°C, causing rapid expansion that creates a shock wave we hear as thunder. Light travels faster than sound, so you see lightning first.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS LIGHTNING</pattern>
<template>Lightning is a massive electrical discharge between clouds or cloud and ground. It can reach 30,000°C (5x hotter than the Sun's surface!), travel at 270,000 mph, and contain 1 billion volts.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS RAIN</pattern>
<template>Rain is liquid water falling from clouds. It forms when water vapor condenses around particles, forming droplets that grow heavy enough to fall. The water cycle: evaporation → condensation → precipitation.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS SNOW</pattern>
<template>Snow is frozen water vapor that forms ice crystals in clouds. Each snowflake is unique due to the complex formation process. Snow reflects 80-90% of sunlight and insulates the ground beneath it.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A RAINBOW</pattern>
<template>A rainbow is an optical phenomenon caused by sunlight refracting, reflecting, and dispersing through water droplets. It always appears opposite the Sun. It's actually a full circle - we only see an arc from ground level!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS PHOTON</pattern>
<template>A photon is a particle of light - the quantum of electromagnetic radiation. It has zero mass, always travels at light speed, and exhibits both wave and particle properties (wave-particle duality). Weird but fundamental!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS AN ELECTRON</pattern>
<template>An electron is a negatively charged subatomic particle that orbits the atomic nucleus. It has almost no mass (1/1836 of a proton). Electron flow is what we call electricity. Essential for chemistry and electronics!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A PROTON</pattern>
<template>A proton is a positively charged subatomic particle in the atomic nucleus. The number of protons defines the element (hydrogen has 1, helium has 2, etc.). Protons are made of quarks.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS A NEUTRON</pattern>
<template>A neutron is a subatomic particle with no charge, found in atomic nuclei alongside protons. It's slightly heavier than a proton. Neutrons help stabilize nuclei - without them, protons would repel each other.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS QUANTUM PHYSICS</pattern>
<template>Quantum physics studies matter and energy at the smallest scales where classical physics breaks down. Things can be waves AND particles, exist in multiple states, and appear to teleport. It's weird but true!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS RELATIVITY</pattern>
<template>Relativity is Einstein's theory describing gravity as curved spacetime and stating that time dilates at high speeds or strong gravity. E=mc² comes from special relativity. GPS satellites must account for it!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS THE BIG BANG</pattern>
<template>The Big Bang is the prevailing theory of the universe's origin - that everything expanded from an incredibly hot, dense point about 13.8 billion years ago. The universe is still expanding today!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS DARK MATTER</pattern>
<template>Dark matter is invisible matter that doesn't emit light but exerts gravitational effects. It makes up about 27% of the universe. We can't see it directly but detect it through its gravitational influence on visible matter.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS DARK ENERGY</pattern>
<template>Dark energy is a mysterious force causing the universe's accelerating expansion. It makes up about 68% of the universe's total energy. We know it exists by its effects but don't know what it actually is!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS SPEED OF LIGHT</pattern>
<template>The speed of light is 299,792,458 meters per second (about 186,000 miles/second) in vacuum. It's the universe's speed limit - nothing with mass can reach it. Light from the Sun takes 8 minutes to reach Earth.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS ABSOLUTE ZERO</pattern>
<template>Absolute zero is the lowest possible temperature: -273.15°C or 0 Kelvin. At this point, atoms have minimal motion. It's physically impossible to reach exactly, but scientists have gotten within billionths of a degree!</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS TEMPERATURE</pattern>
<template>Temperature is a measure of the average kinetic energy of particles in a substance. Higher temperature = faster particle movement. Measured in Celsius, Fahrenheit, or Kelvin.</template>
</category>

<category><pattern>WHAT IS PRESSURE</pattern>
<template>Pressure is force per unit area. Atmospheric pressure is caused by air's weight pressing down. At sea level, it's about 14.7 pounds per square inch. Pressure affects boiling points and weather patterns.</template>
</category>

</aiml>
